Finding Aid for Gardner Stewart Williams papers 1900-1945
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gardner Stewart Williams Papers 1900-1945
Williams, Gardner Stewart, 1866-1931.
21.5 GB online
7 oversize folders
7 linear feet (in 8 boxes)
85544 Aa 2 UAl
Ann Arbor, Michigan based hydraulic engineer known for his multiple arch dams, hydroelectric plants, and for developing the Hazen-Williams hydraulic tables, designed and consulted on numerous water power and dam projects. Papers include biographical files, material relating to construction of dams and power plants on the Huron River and elsewhere, and papers relating to Michigan Engineering Society.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received from the Ann Arbor engineering firm, Ayres, Lewis, Norris and May in December 1981 (donor no. 5642 ). In 2011, an additional volume was donated by Bill Wheeler (donor no. 10511 ).
The collection is open for research.
Gardner Stewart Williams was born in Saginaw, Michigan, in 1866. He was graduated from Saginaw City High School in 1884, and received a degree in civil engineering from the University of Michigan in 1889.
Williams became a nationally recognized authority in hydraulic engineering, and was known for his multiple arch dams, hydroelectric plants, and for developing the Hazen-Williams hydraulic tables. He was employed as an engineer on water works construction at Bismarck, North Dakota, and at Greenville and Owosso, Michigan. From 1890 to 1893 he was a draftsman and engineer with the Russell Wheel and Foundry Company of Detroit, and from 1893 to 1898 was civil engineer to the Detroit Board of Water Commissioners. It was while he was in Detroit that he developed the valuable Hazen-Williams Tables, which calculate the headloss in pipes.
From 1898 to 1904 Williams was professor of experimental hydraulics and engineer in charge of the hydraulic laboratory at Cornell University, and from 1904 to 1911 was professor of civil, hydraulic and sanitary engineering at the University of Michigan.
Williams had been a consulting engineering since 1895, and was in increasing demand as a consultant. In 1911 he resigned from the University and devoted full time to his consulting practice. He opened his first office with Robert Norris, a former student, as a subordinate. From 1911 to 1931 Williams had a wide range of engineering interests, and his company had offices in Ann Arbor and Chicago. In addition to being an engineering consultant, Williams acted as an agent for his hydroelectric clients and purchased the flowage rights along various rivers. He also became known as an expert witness and testified in court cases throughout the United States about the causes of hydraulic failures. In 1923 his consulting firm formed a partnership known as Ayres, Lewis, Norris and May. Williams, however, preferred to remain as an independent consultant.
Among his many accomplishments, Williams designed the single arch Cheeseborough Dam in Ithaca, New York, in 1906; the multiple arch dam at Sturgis, Michigan, which was built in 1910; and the water power plant at Sault Ste. Marie. In 1930 he designed the Magnitogorsky Dam on the Ural River in Siberia, Russia.
As consultant for the Detroit Edison Company, Williams prepared a proposal for the development of the Huron River water powers. By 1910 Detroit Edison, with Williams acting as their agent, had acquired most of the prospective flowage rights necessary for the project. The Huron River development was not completed as planned, but six dams were built: Barton in 1912, Argo in 1913, Geddes in 1916, Superior in 1919, French Landing in 1925, and Rawsonville (owned by Henry Ford) in 1927.
Williams died in 1931.
The Gardner Stewart William papers, 1900-1931 are arranged in five series:
Biographical and Historical Material
Power Plants and Dams
Huron River Power Plants and Dams
Other Power Plants and Dams
Detroit Edison Company
Engineering Reports
Photographs
The papers of Gardner Williams, 1900-1931, include biographical material; papers relating to the history of Michigan Engineering Society; project files detailing construction of Huron River power plants and dams at Argo, Barton, Geddes, Superior, and French Landing; other Michigan project files for dams and plants in Sault Ste. Marie and elsewhere; Detroit Edison consultation materials; engineering reports by, or including comments of, Williams; and photographs.
The Williams papers came from the offices of Ayres, Lewis, Norris and May, Ann Arbor engineering firm. Obviously a fragment, they cover only the period of 1900 to 1931, with photographs spanning the dates 1900 to 1945.
The collection begins with a folder of biographical material and a folder regarding the history of the Michigan Engineering Society. Except for these, the collection divides into four series: Power Plants and Dams, the Detroit Edison Company, Engineering Reports, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Dams.; Detroit Edison Company.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); Michigan Engineering Society.; Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.); Water power.
Subjects - Visual Material
Adrian (Mich.); Alma (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Waterworks.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Argo Dam (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Augusta (Mich.); Bad Axe (Mich.); Bangor (Mich.); Barton Dam (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Bay City (Mich.); Beaverton (Mich.); Belle Isle Bridge (Detroit, Mich.); Belleville (Mich.); Berrien Springs (Mich.); Birmingham (Mich.); Black River (Mich.); Boyne Falls (Mich.); Breedsville (Mich.); Bridges.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Cadillac (Mich.); Ceresco (Mich.); Clare (Mich.); Clinton River (Mich.); Construction industry.; Croswell (Mich.); Dams.; Delhi (Mich.); Detroit Edison Company.; Dowagiac (Mich.); Dundee (Mich.); Edenville (Mich.); Elsie (Mich.); Freeport (Mich.); Geddes Dam (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Gladwin County (Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Grosse Pointe Farms (Mich.); Heating Plant (University of Michigan); Homer (Mich.); Howard City (Mich.); Howell (Mich.); Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); Ionia (Mich.); Kalamazoo (Mich.); Laborers.; Leonidas (Mich.); Lowell (Mich.); Milford (Mich.); Mottville (Mich.); Mount Pleasant (Mich.); Osborne's Mill (Mich.); Otsego (Mich.); Plainwell (Mich.); Port Huron (Mich.); Rawsonville (Mich.); Sanford (Mich.: Village); Saint Joseph River (Mich. and Ind.); Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.); Scotts (Mich.); Sturgis (Mich.); Superior Dam (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Traverse City (Mich.); Water distribution systems.; Waterworks--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Williams, Gardner Stewart, 1866-1931.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Business enterprises.
Contributors:
Ayres, Lewis, Norris, and May.
Genre/Form:
Albums.; Photographs.
- Biographical and Historical Materials
  - Biographical Material (Box 1)
  - History of the Michigan Engineering Society (Box 1)
- Power Plants and Dams
  - Huron River Power Plants and Dams
    Power Plants and Dams relates to dams and plants along the Huron River as well as to other water development projects in Michigan. These files consist of business correspondence on matters of land purchases and flowage rights, blueprints and drawings, contract documents and specifications, computations, and tests. Some of the Huron River projects documented include Argo, Barton, Geddes, Superior and French Landing. Some of the other files concern projects in Allegan, Alpena, Hart, Lowell, Rawsonville, and Sault Ste. Marie. Included with this subgroup are files relating to tests and experiments with draft tubes and the design of multiple arch dams.
    - Land Purchases 1905-1927 (Box 1)
    - Maps of the Huron River Valley from Surveys made in 1908, 1909 (Box 1)
    - Reports
      - Preliminary Report of the Proposed Development of the Huron River Water Powers 1912 (Box 1)
      - Cost New and Cost Less Depreciation of Huron River Power Plants 1915 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous Reports 1917-1930 (Box 1)
    - Barton
      - Contracts and Specifications 1911-1915 (Box 1)
      - Drawings and Computations 1912-1919 (Box 1)
      - Property and Correspondence 1912-1918 (Box 1)
      - Reports 1911, 1916 (Box 1)
      - Sketches 1911-1915 (Box 1)
      - Tests 1913-1915 (Box 1)
    - Argo
      - Computations 1913 (Box 1)
      - Contracts and Specifications 1913 (Box 1)
      - Contracts and Specifications, Power House 1913 (Box 1)
      - Drawings 1911-1915 (Box 1)
      - Head Race, Tail Race, and Canal 1912-1914 (Box 1)
      - Property undated, 1917 (Box 1)
      - Spillway Calculations 1912-1913 (Box 1)
      - Tests 1914-1915 (Box 1)
    - Geddes
      - Computations 1916-1917 (Box 2)
      - Contracts and Specifications 1917-1918 (Box 2)
      - Drawings 1916-1925 (Box 2)
      - Tests 1918 (Box 2)
    - Superior
      - Computations
        - 1907-1914 (Box 2)
        - 1918-1919 (Box 2)
      - Contracts and Specifications
        - Undated, 1914 (Box 2)
        - 1916-1922 (Box 2)
      - Drawings 1914-1922 (Box 2)
    - French Landing
      - Computations 1922-1924 (Box 2)
      - Contracts and Specifications 1924 (Box 2)
      - Drawings 1924-1925 (Box 2)
      - Sketches 1924-1925 (Box 2)
  - Other Power Plants and Dams
    - Allegan
      - Computations 1927-1931 (Box 2)
      - Reports and drawings 1926-1929 (Box 2)
    - Alpena
      - Field Notes 1923-1952 (Box 2)
      - Maps, Prints, Miscellaneous 1916-1952 (Box 2)
    - Delhi
      - Drawings 1913-1915 (Box 3)
      - Property 1915-1922 (Box 3)
    - Hart
      - Business Correspondence
        - 1923-1926 (Box 3)
        - 1924-1926 (Box 3)
        - 1927-1928 (Box 3)
      - Clippings (Box 3)
      - Maps and Drawings (Box 3)
      - Reports 1923-1924 (Box 3)
    - Lowell
      - Business Correspondence 1929-1930 (Box 3)
      - Computations 1929 (Box 3)
      - Drawings 1930 (Box 3)
      - Specifications 1917 (Box 3)
    - Rawsonville (Ford Motor Company)
      - Contract and Correspondence 1930-1932 (Box 3)
      - Drawings 1910-1928 (Box 3)
    - Sault Ste. Marie
      - Clippings (Box 3)
      - Computations 1905-1911 (Box 3)
      - Drawings (Box 3)
      - Financial Records 1903-1911 (Box 3)
      - Testimony of Gardner Stewart Williams (Box 3)
    - Scio
      - Drawings 1909 (Box 3)
      - Property 1913-1923 (Box 3)
  - Blueprints
    - Midway, Alpena, Alcona 1922-1924 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      (includes photographs)
    - Draft Tubes - Tests and Experiments (Box 4)
    - Multiple Arch Dams (Box 4)
- Detroit Edison Company
  The Detroit Edison series contains correspondence relating to land purchases, reports, and a company history.
  - Property
    - 1912-1924 (Box 4)
    - 1925-1931 (Box 4)
  - Reports and Company History (Box 4)
- Engineering Reports
  The Reports series consists of reports either written by Williams or commented upon by him. Most concern Michigan projects and relate to the development of water power.
  - Experimental Investigation Upon the Measurement of Discharge of Turbine Wheels made for the Michigan Lake Superior Power Company 1900 (Box 4)
  - The Applicability of the Francis Formula for the Flow of Water over Weirs to the conditions existing at the Holyoke Testing Flume 1901 (Box 4)
  - The Flow of Water over Weirs 1905 (Box 4)
  - The Tittabawassee River Water Power 1909 (Box 4)
  - The Grand Rapids Water Power 1910 (Box 4)
  - The Tittabawassee River Water Power 1911 (Box 4)
  - Reports on the Valuation and Extension of the Ann Arbor Water Works 1912 (Box 4)
  - Water Power of the Tittabawassee River 1913 (Box 4)
  - The Tittabawassee River Water Power 1915 (Box 4)
  - The Electrical Department of the Sanitary District of Chicago, Account Classification 1916 (Box 4)
  - Preliminary and Supplementary Report to the Great Northern Power Company Upon the Development of Additional Power 1919 (Box 4)
  - A Brief Upon the Potential Water Power of the Great Lakes - St. Lawrence Waterway 1921 (Box 4)
  - Special Report on the Proposed Water Power Development on the St. Louis River near Scanlon, Minnesota 1921 (Box 4)
  - Report on the Storage Requirements at the Thomson Plant of the Great Northern Power Company 1922 (Box 4)
  - A Study of the Flow of Water over Weirs 1924 (Box 4)
  - Report on the Valuation of the Property of the Beaverton Power Company 1924 (Box 4)
  - A Municipal Hydroelectric Plant-Replacing Steam by Water Power in the City of Sturgis, Michigan undated (Box 4)
  - Hydraulic tables (Box 4)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (1900-1945) includes albums and other photographs of dam construction and other construction projects in Michigan and elsewhere, especially the Argo, Barton, Geddes, and Superior dams on the Huron River, and photographs of rivers and riverside scenes as they existed before dam construction began.
  - Class reunions
    - Classes of 1888 and 1905 (Box 5)
  - Projects (also see Albums)
    - Ann Arbor. Argo Mills (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor. Barton Dam, 8 folders (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor. Geddes project (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor. Huron River Sewage Pumping Station (Box 5)
      (work of Ayres, Lewis, Norris and May)
    - Ithaca, New York, Water works and Cornell Filter (Box 5)
    - Lowell project (Box 5)
    - Sault Ste. Marie project (Box 5)
    - Sault Ste. Marie. Description of photos (Box 5)
      (most not received)
    - Sturgis project (Box 5)
    - Superior project (Box 5)
    - Unidentified (Box 5)
  - Albums
    - Argo Mills 1909-1914 (Box 5)
    - Barton Dam 1912-1923 (Box 5)
    - Des Moines Electric Company 1916-1918 (Box 5)
    - French Landing Project 1918-1926 (Box 8)
      photos have been removed from album for preservation; donor no. 10511.
    - Geddes Dam 1914-1925 (Box 6)
    - Sturgis 1910-1912 (Box 6)
    - Superior 1901-1912 (Box 6)
    - Superior 1919-1922 (Box 6)
      (tagged 4a)
    - Miscellaneous A 1909-1945 (Box 7)
      (tagged 27)
      - Gladwin County (Box 7)
        (including views of the Tittabawassee River at Edenville and Sanford and other rivers in Gladwin County)
      - Ionia (Box 7)
      - Croswell (Box 7)
      - Port Huron Water Works (Box 7)
      - Bad Axe (Box 7)
      - Cadillac (Box 7)
      - Bay City State Park (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous B 1914-1923
      - Clinton River (Box 7)
      - Consolidated Light and Power Company (Box 7)
      - Dundee (Box 7)
      - Howell (Box 7)
      - Berrien Springs (Box 7)
      - Traverse City (Box 7)
      - Black River (Box 7)
      - Peninsular Paper Company Mill, Ypsilanti (Box 7)
      - Ypsilanti (Box 7)
      - Oak Knitting Company, Ypsilanti (Box 7)
      - Detroit-Port Huron Pipeline (Box 7)
        (including views of Clinton River at Mount Clemens)
      - Monarch Paper Company, Kalamazoo (Box 7)
      - Dowagiac (Box 7)
      - Leonidas
      - Bangor (Box 7)
      - Breedsville (Box 7)
      - Augusta (Box 7)
      - Scotts (Box 7)
      - Homer (Box 7)
      - Mottville (Box 7)
      - Ceresco (Box 7)
      - Loveland, Ohio (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous C 1914-1920
      - Spooner, Wisconsin (Box 7)
      - Mt. Pleasant (Box 7)
      - Clare (Box 7)
      - Alma (Box 7)
      - Watab Pulp and Paper Company (Box 7)
      - Grosse Pointe Farms (Pipeline) (Box 7)
    - Album No. 16 1904-1924
      - Maple River (Box 7)
      - Tower Dam (Box 7)
      - Elsie (Box 7)
      - Freeport (Box 7)
      - Alma (Box 7)
      - Grand Rapids (Box 7)
      - Puget Sound Electric Light & Power Co. (R.C. Starr) (Box 7)
      - Three Rivers (Box 7)
      - Howard City (Box 7)
      - Dixon Dam, Dixon, Illinois (Box 7)
      - Plainwell, Michigan (Box 7)
      - Cedar Rapids, Iowa (Box 7)
      - Peshtigo River, Wisconsin (Box 7)
      - Northern Hydro-Electric Power Company, Peshtigo River, Wisconsin (Box 7)
      - Campbells Arch Dam - Cascadilla Gorge, Ithaca, New York (Box 7)
      - Stanwood Dam (Box 7)
      - Fond Du Lac Dam Site (Box 7)
      - Birmingham - Quarton Lake Dam (Box 7)
      - Otsego (Box 7)
      - Belle Isle Bridge (Box 7)
      - Syracuse (Box 7)
      - Beaverton (Box 7)
      - Boyne Falls (Box 7)
      - Adrian Gas Appraisal (Box 7)
    - Album No. 17 1908-1925
      - Osborne (Box 7)
      - Delhi (Box 7)
      - Edison Company lot at Ypsilanti (Box 7)
      - Rawsonville (Box 7)
      - Belleville (Box 7)
      - Wayne (Box 7)
      - Hamburg (Box 7)
      - Milford (Box 7)
      - Ann Arbor Water Works (Box 7)
      - Pontney Well-Steere Farm Case (Box 7)
      - Detroit Edison Company (Box 7)
      - Dundee Dam (Box 7)
      - Huron Farms Company, Barton Road Bridge (Box 7)
      - Huron River at Grisson's Bridge (Box 7)
      - Raisin River Power Plant (Box 7)
      - University of Michigan Substation (Box 7)
      - McHenry (Box 7)
- Huron River Survey Maps
  Gardner Williams surveyed the Huron River in Washtenaw and Wayne Counties between 1905 and 1909 for the Eastern Michigan Edison Company. The Huron River Survey Maps series contains original maps and some copies from these surveys. Each map is numbered, but does not include a distinctive title. For this finding aid we have provided titles based on a landmark found on each map. The Bentley Historical Library also holds a photographically reproduced set of these maps at a smaller size (MH 4 W319 1909 W723). The original maps in this collection include later additions and changes not found on the photographic copies. Scanned images of the maps are linked from the descriptions below.
  - Original maps
    - Upstream from Ypsilanti
      - 5101 [Ypsilanti] (Folder 1)
      - 5102 [Leforge Road] (Folder 1)
      - 5103 [Superior Pond] (Folder 1)
      - 5104 [Fleming Creek] (Folder 1)
      - 5105 [Vivienne Farm] (Folder 1)
      - 5106 [Geddes Pond] (Folder 2)
      - 5107 [Arboretum] (Folder 2)
      - 5108 [Ann Arbor] (Folder 2)
        (this map is available only as copies in folder 7)
      - 5109 [Argo Pond]
      - 5110 [Barton Hills] 1905 (Folder 2)
      - 5110 [Barton Hills] 1911 (Folder 2)
      - 5111 [Fosters] (Folder 3)
      - 5112 [Delhi] (Folder 3)
      - 5113 [Scio] (Folder 3)
      - 5114 [Dexter East] (Folder 3)
      - 5115 [Dexter West] (Folder 4)
      - 5116 [Between Dexter and Hudson Mills] (Folder 4)
      - 5117 [Between Dexter and Hudson Mills] (Folder 4)
      - 5118 [Hudson Mills] (Folder 4)
      - 5119 [Portage Lake] (Folder 4)
    - Downstream from Ypsilanti
      - 5120 [Ypsilanti] (Folder 5)
      - 5121 [Ypsilanti South] (Folder 5)
        (this map is only available as a photographic reproduction, see MH 4 W319 1909 W723)
      - 5122 [Whittaker Road-Huron River Drive] (Folder 5)
      - 5123 [Tuttle Hill Road-Harris Road] (Folder 5)
      - 5124 [Rawsonville West] (Folder 5)
      - 5125 [Rawsonville East] (Folder 5)
      - 5126 [Belleville West] (Folder 6)
      - 5127 [Belleville East] (Folder 6)
      - 5128 [French Landing] (Folder 6)
    - Other maps
      - 5134 [Barton Hills] 1916 (Folder 6)
      - Village of Rawsonville 1922 (Folder 6)
  - Copies
    - Upstream from Ypsilanti
      - 5107 [Arboretum] (Folder 7)
      - 5108 [Ann Arbor] (copy 1) (Folder 7)
      - 5108 [Ann Arbor] (copy 2 showing changes to the channel below Argo Dam) (Folder 7)
      - 5119 [Portage Lake] (Folder 7)
    - Downstream from Ypsilanti
      - 5124 [Rawsonville West] (Folder 7)
  - Composite Map
    - Huron River Watershed
      A digital composite map of the Huron River Watershed was created from Bentley Historical Library scans of maps from the Gardner S. Williams collection. The composite image created by Huron River Watershed Council staff.